<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Fresh water system</title>

  <para>The fresh water system consists of two 1680 litre stainless-steel
  fixed storage tanks, a hydrophore with a 230VAC electrical pump and an
  on-demand, plate heat-exchanger based, hot water generator.</para>

  <para>Refer to <xref linkend="fluid-storage-and-handling"/> for a system
  overview.</para>

  <para>The twin tanks are normally commoned through valves located under the
  saloon floor: it is possible to operate the system from just one tank by
  closing the appropriate valves between tanks and on the commoning
  manifold.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Filling the tanks</title>

    <para>Ensure that the hose you use for topping up your potable water tanks
    is appropriate for potable water and that your chosen water water source
    is in fact dispensing drinking water.</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Locate the deck filler marked "WATER".</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Clean the area around the filler and ensure that any adjacent
        filler caps are firmly closed.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Clean the end of the hose which will be inserted into the ship's
        filler port and run water through the hose for a sufficient time to
        eliminate any retained or static water from the supply.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Open the deck filler, insert the hose and commence
        filling.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Fill the tank. Do not overfill - a 90% reading on the tank gauge
        is a sensible target.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Remove the hose and replace the filler cap.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Make an entry in the ship's log.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Tank level monitoring</title>

    <para>Each tank is equipped with an electronic tank level monitoring
    system consisting of a hydrostatic tank level sender which broadcasts
    messages onto the ship's domestic NMEA 2000 bus. Tank level data can be
    displayed on screens located at the helm, domestic panel and
    elsewhere.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                     fileref="resources/images/DIN_4844-2/warning/W000_general.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject> Variations in tank level readings are possible due
    to conditions of trim, list, seaway and calibration.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                     fileref="resources/images/DIN_4844-2/warning/W000_general.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject> Tank level sensing requires <guilabel>NMEA BUS
    0</guilabel> to be enabled on the ship's domestic panel.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                     fileref="resources/images/DIN_4844-2/mandatory/M018_read_manual.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject> <citation>mare1</citation></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Pressure system</title>

    <para>The ship's hydrophore is installed in the engine room and consists
    of a 230VAC electrically driven pump and pressure vessel. The system is
    set to a default pressure of 3 bar and will automatically maintain this,
    starting the pump as necessary to cater for demand.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                     fileref="resources/images/IEC5010/IEC5010_On_Off_Symbol%20.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject>To enable and disable the pressure system use the
    switch labelled <guilabel>HYDROPHORE</guilabel> on the ship's domestic
    panel, but note that the system is entirely automatic in operation and it
    is recommended that the hydrophore remain powered at all times.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                     fileref="resources/images/DIN_4844-2/warning/W000_general.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject> The pressure system can only be enable and disabled
    if <guilabel>NMEA BUS 0</guilabel> is enabled.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                     fileref="resources/images/DIN_4844-2/warning/W025_risk_of_remote_start.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject> The motor and pump have an exposed mechanism and
    may begin operation unexpectedly.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                     fileref="resources/images/DIN_4844-2/warning/W008_risk_of_electrocution.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject> Danger of electrical shock 230VAC</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                     fileref="resources/images/DIN_4844-2/mandatory/M018_read_manual.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject> <citation>spec1</citation></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Hot water</title>

    <para>Hot water is generated by a heat exchanger system located in the
    engine-room. When a hot-water tap is opened fluid from the ship's thermal
    buffer is pumped through the heat exchanger primary circuit and used to
    heat cold water, delivered by the hydrophore, in the heat exchanger
    secondary circuit.</para>

    <para>An independent pumped hot-water loop is triggered by operation of a
    light switch in the day heads and en-suite and ensures that, under most
    circumstances, pre-heated water is available at an outlet in anticipation
    of its likely use.</para>

    <para>When the thermal buffer is fully charged it can supply enough hot
    water for at least a day's normal domestic usage without the input of any
    additional energy.</para>

    <para>If the thermal buffer is cold, then it can be recharged for the
    purpose of hot water generation almost instantaneously from the ship's
    boiler or less rapidly by use of the immersion heaters (waste heat from
    operation of the main engine and generator is also used to recharge the
    buffer). Refer to <xref linkend="heating"/> for detailed information on
    managing the thermal buffer.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                     fileref="resources/images/IEC5010/IEC5010_On_Off_Symbol%20.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject> To enable and disable the hot-water system use the
    switch marked <guilabel>THERMAL STORE</guilabel> on the ship's domestic
    panel.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                     fileref="resources/images/IEC5010/IEC5010_On_Off_Symbol%20.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject> To enable and disable the hot-water loop use the
    switch marked <guilabel>HOT WATER LOOP</guilabel> on the ship's domestic
    panel.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                     fileref="resources/images/DIN_4844-2/warning/W000_general.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject> The hot-water system and hot-water loop can only be
    enabled and disabled if <guilabel>NMEA BUS 0</guilabel> is enabled.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                     fileref="resources/images/DIN_4844-2/mandatory/M018_read_manual.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject> FILL ME IN</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Heads</title>

    <para>WCs on the vessel are operated electrically and flush from the
    ship's fresh water system, discharging directly into the ship's black
    water holding tank. The WC units are operated by a simple flush button and
    consume either 3 litres of 5 litres of water per operation depending on
    the selected flush mode.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                     fileref="resources/images/DIN_4844-2/warning/W008_risk_of_electrocution.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject> WC units operate at 230VAC, unplug from mains
    before servicing.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                     fileref="resources/images/DIN_4844-2/mandatory/M018_read_manual.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject> <citation>sani1</citation></para>
  </section>
</section>
