<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Vessel type and identification</title>

  <section>
    <title>Craft Identification Number</title>

    <para>The Craft Identification Number (CIN) (formerly known as the Hull
    Identification Number (HIN)) is affixed on the upper starboard side of the
    transom of the boat.</para>

    <para>Data from which the CIN is composed are: producer, type of boat,
    yard build number, year of construction and model year.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="1cm"
                     fileref="RESOURCES/images/DIN_4844-2/mandatory/M000_general.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject> Do not alter, remove or damage the CIN.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Builder's plate</title>

    <para>The builder's plate is affixed at the helm and contains valuable
    information on your vessel including the name of builder, CE-mark, design
    category, maximum recommended number of persons when under way and maximum
    recommended load. These last two data items should be understood in
    conjunction with the vessel loading information given elsewhere in this
    manual.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="1cm"
                     fileref="RESOURCES/images/DIN_4844-2/mandatory/M000_general.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject> Do not alter, remove or damage the builder's
    plate.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Vessel design category</title>

    <para>The design category is assigned to the boat by the producer of the
    boat. For your ship, the design category is given on the Declaration of
    Conformity (DOC), please refer to section 7.</para>

    <para>Design categories are defined in the European Boating Directive in
    the following way:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>A. OCEAN</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Designed for extended voyages where conditions may exceed wind
          force 8 (Beaufort scale) and significant wave heights of 4 m and
          above, and vessels largely self-sufficient.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>B. OFFSHORE</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Designed for offshore voyages where conditions up to, and
          including, wind force 8 and significant wave heights up to, and
          including, 4 m may be experienced.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>C. INSHORE</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Designed for voyages in coastal waters, large bays, estuaries,
          lakes and rivers where conditions up to, and including, wind force 6
          and significant wave heights up to, and including, 2 m may be
          experienced.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>D. SHELTERED WATERS</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Designed for voyages on small lakes, rivers, and canals where
          conditions up to, and including, wind force 4 and significant wave
          heights up to, and including, 0,5 m may be experienced.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>Your ship is built to exact standards, and complies with the
    essential requirements of the European Boating Directive which lays down
    requirements for stability, buoyancy, construction, installations,
    etc.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
