<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Deckwash</title>

  <para>The ship's deckwash system serves two auto-stop hose connector outlets
  located on the aft-deck and fore-deck lockers.</para>

  <para>Both outlets are fed with fresh water from the ship's pressurised
  domestic water system, but the aft outlet can be reconfigured to supply raw
  water.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Using raw water at the aft deckwash outlet</title>

    <para>To use raw water at the aft deckwash outlet:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Close the freshwater shut-off valve located on the engine-room
        deckhead just aft of the engine-room hatch.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Open the through-hull sea cock supplying the chiller unit raw
        water intake. </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Open the deckwash pump supply valve on the output side of the
        raw water intake filter. </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Switch on the <keycap>D.WASH</keycap> switch at the helm to
        enable the deckwash pump.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>The deckwash pump is self-priming and will operate automatically to
    maintain pressure at the deckwash aft outlet.</para>

    <para>To avoid the possibility of leak you should switch off the deckwash
    pump when it is not in use.</para>

    <para>To avoid the possibility of raw water contaminating the ship's
    freshwater system you must ensure that freshwater shut-off valve is closed
    when the raw water pump is in use. An automatic double-check valve
    provides a passive fallback, but it is best not to rely on this as the
    primary means of isolation. </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Winterisation</title>

    <para>In freezing weather, the above deck pipework should be drained down
    through the bleed and isolation valves located in the engine room and the
    master cabin wardrobe.</para>
  </section>
</section>
