<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Electrical system</title>

  <para>The vessel has three discrete electrical systems as summarised
  below.</para>

  <informaltable>
    <tgroup cols="5">
      <thead>
        <row>
          <entry>System</entry>

          <entry>Rating</entry>

          <entry>Battery</entry>

          <entry>Charged by</entry>

          <entry>Master switch</entry>
        </row>
      </thead>

      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry>Generator engine</entry>

          <entry>12VDC</entry>

          <entry>1 x 12VDC 120Ah</entry>

          <entry>Generator alternator</entry>

          <entry>Engine room (aft switch)</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry/>

          <entry/>

          <entry/>

          <entry>12VDC battery charger</entry>

          <entry/>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry>Main engine</entry>

          <entry>24VDC</entry>

          <entry>2 x 12VDC 120Ah</entry>

          <entry>Main engine alternator</entry>

          <entry>Engine room (forward switch)</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry/>

          <entry/>

          <entry/>

          <entry>24VDC battery charger</entry>

          <entry/>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry>Domestic</entry>

          <entry>24VDC</entry>

          <entry>12 x 2VDC 1100Ah</entry>

          <entry>Main engine alternator</entry>

          <entry>Battery compartment</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry/>

          <entry/>

          <entry/>

          <entry>24VDC battery charger</entry>

          <entry/>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry/>

          <entry/>

          <entry/>

          <entry>Solar charge controller</entry>

          <entry/>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry/>

          <entry>230VAC</entry>

          <entry>n/a</entry>

          <entry>n/a</entry>

          <entry>n/a</entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </informaltable>

  <section>
    <title>Generator engine system</title>

    <para>The generator engine system is entirely self-contained with no
    consumers other than the generator and its control panel.</para>

    <para>A single 12VDC 120Ah battery and associated master switch are
    located below the generator housing on the port side of the engine
    room.</para>

    <para>The generator battery is charged from the generator alternator and
    from a separate 230VAC battery charger located next to the battery. The
    battery charger is only energised when the ship is on shore or generator
    power.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Main engine system</title>

    <para>The main engine system operates at 24VDC and supports the main
    engine and its control panel, propeller shaft lubrication pump, raw-water
    deck-wash pump and the stern navigation light.</para>

    <para>Two 12VDC 120Ah series-connected batteries and associated master
    switch are located below the generator housing on the port side of the
    engine room.</para>

    <para>The main engine batteries are charged via a split-charge controller
    from the main engine alternator (the residual charging current is used to
    charge the ship's domestic battery bank) and from a separate 230VAC
    battery charger located next to the batteries. The battery charger is only
    energised when the ship is on shore or generator power.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Domestic system</title>

    <para>The domestic system consists of a 24VDC house battery bank connected
    to a 230VAC inverter-charger. This integrated system supports all domestic
    and navigation electrical systems: there is no bias towards the use of DC
    or AC for particular purposes and individual equipment is specified for AC
    or DC connection based on technical, performance and efficiency
    considerations.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Domestic DC system</title>

      <para>The domestic DC system operates at 24VDC and supports all ship's
      systems which require a direct current supply (other than those
      supported by the generator and main engine systems discussed
      above).</para>

      <para>Twelve 2VDC 1100Ah series connected batteries and associated
      master switch are located in the battery compartment below the galley
      floor.</para>

      <para>The house batteries are charged by an integrated 8kW
      inverter-charger and 5kW solar charge controller.</para>

      <para>The inverter-charger automatically blends inverting and charging
      depending upon consumer demand and the availability of an external
      230VAC power source, but can be switched to charger-only mode using the
      control mounted in the domestic panel. Two 230VAC energy inputs are
      available: a shore-power connection on the aft deck allows connection to
      a utility outlet and supplies energy to the inverter-charger through a
      7kW isolating transformer; the ship's generator can provide up to 12kW
      of energy when off-grid.</para>

      <para>The solar charge controller connects to a 1kW solar panel array
      mounted over the aft deck.</para>

      <para>The main DC connection box integrates all suppliers and
      consumers</para>

      <para>are of can be switched between charge only and inverter-charge
      only energised when the the ship is connected to a 230VAC shore power
      supply or when the ship's generator is running.</para>

      <para>A direct connection from the battery isolator switch powers Busbar
      1 which supports connection of services which should be permanently
      available even when the boat is out of service. This includes
      connections to charging sources (charger/inverter, main engine
      alternator and solar charge controller) and some safety critical
      consumers (helm-panel essential services like bilge pumps and alarms and
      spudpole). Individual isolators can be operated to disconnect these
      consumers if required.</para>

      <para>A second connection from the battery isolator switch goes via an
      isolator to Busbar 2 which supports connection of all non-essential
      consumers. This isolator can be operated remotely from the domestic
      panel <literal>MAIN ISOLATOR</literal> control.</para>

      <para><mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="RESOURCES/DC1.pdf"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Batteries and master switch</title>

      <para>Twelve 2VDC 1100Ah series-connected batteries and associated
      master switch are located in the battery compartment below the galley
      floor.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Main distribution board</title>

      <para>The main distribution board is supplied from the main isolator
      switch and is configured in three circuit groups each with differing
      isolation possibilities. See</para>

      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="4">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Fuse (circuit)</entry>

              <entry>Fuse rating/A</entry>

              <entry>Group</entry>

              <entry>Remark</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>F1 Inverter/charger</entry>

              <entry>250</entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry/>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>F2 Inverter/charger</entry>

              <entry>250</entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry/>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>F3 Spud pole</entry>

              <entry>150</entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry/>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>F4 Alternator</entry>

              <entry>150</entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry/>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>F5 Helm B</entry>

              <entry>150</entry>

              <entry>Helm non-essential services (all helm panel functions
              with the exception of bilge and alarm systems).</entry>

              <entry>Group can be isolated locally at distribution board and
              remotely by the <keycap>DC ISOL</keycap> control on the domestic
              panel.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>F6 Cabinet C3</entry>

              <entry>100</entry>

              <entry>""</entry>

              <entry/>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>F7 (spare)</entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry>""</entry>

              <entry/>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>F8 (spare)</entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry>""</entry>

              <entry/>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>F9 Helm A</entry>

              <entry>100</entry>

              <entry>Helm essential services (bilge and alarm systems
              only).</entry>

              <entry>Group can be isolated locally at distribution
              board.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>

      <para/>

      <para/>

      <para/>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title/>

      <para/>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Domestic 230VAC system</title>

    <para>The ship's 230VAC system supports most domestic consumer functions
    including hydrophore, heating, cooling, ventilation, galley refrigeration,
    interior lighting, WC and waste sumps. The supply-side of the system is
    controlled by an integrated charger-inverter monitored and operated from
    the domestic panel.</para>

    <para>All outgoing circuits are routed through the main distribution
    cabinet C1 to a collection (C2, C4, C5a and C5b) of sub-cabinets which
    feed individual consumer circuits. All circuits are fused by circuit
    breaker and single-pole residual current protection.</para>

    <para>Residual current safety features are only functional if the
    shore-power connection is properly polarised.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Energy sources</title>

      <para>The following table lists available energy sources. The ship's
      systems are configured to automatically select the energy source with
      the lowest priority number when it is available. The charger/inverter is
      able to concurrently top-up any shortfall in generator or shore supply
      by inversion.</para>

      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="6">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Source</entry>

              <entry>Rating/kVA</entry>

              <entry>Device</entry>

              <entry>Priority</entry>

              <entry>Control principle</entry>

              <entry>Isolation</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Generator</entry>

              <entry>12</entry>

              <entry>Diesel generator set</entry>

              <entry>1</entry>

              <entry>The generator is started manually by operation of the
              helm control panel or the <keycap>GENERATOR</keycap> control on
              the domestic panel. Automatic generator start is possible (see ?
              and the</entry>

              <entry>Disconnect isolator switch in engine room.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Shore power</entry>

              <entry>7</entry>

              <entry>Isolating transformer</entry>

              <entry>2</entry>

              <entry>Shore power is automatically enabled when the shore power
              connection is plugged in.</entry>

              <entry>Disconnect isolator switch in engine room.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Domestic battery set</entry>

              <entry>8</entry>

              <entry>Charger-inverter</entry>

              <entry>3</entry>

              <entry>The charge function is permanently enabled and can only
              be defeated by isolating the domestic battery bank. The inverter
              function can be disabled by the charger-inverter control panel
              on the domestic panel.</entry>

              <entry>Main battery isolator.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>230VAC distribution</title>

      <para/>

      <section>
        <title>Distribution cabinet C1</title>

        <para>Distribution cabinet C1 is the upper of the two cabinets
        installed in the forward bulkhead of the lower deck lobby and is the
        ship's main AC distribution cabinet.</para>

        <para>The cabinet receives two 230VAC supplies directly from the
        ship's inverter/charger. A no-break supply (via isolator (1)) feeds
        all of the cabinet devices, deriving power from the currently selected
        source. A second supply (via isolator (6)) derives power from shore
        and generator only and routes this directly to cabinet C5a since the
        only consumers of this supply are located in the ship's engine
        room.</para>

        <para>All circuits in the cabinet are overload and leakage protected.
        Four RCBO devices at the top-right of the cabinet supply individual
        circuits making these consumers insensitive to failures in other
        circuits and to nuisance tripping. Four outgoing circuits (protected
        by (2)) supply downstream distribution cabinets with circuits
        protected by (3), (4) and (5) supplying consumers in the galley and
        lower-deck.</para>

        <figure xml:id="distribution_cabinet_c1">
          <title>Distribution cabinet C1</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="left" contentwidth="10cm"
                         fileref="RESOURCES/distribution_cabinet_c1.png"
                         xml:id="distribution_cabinet_c1"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Distribution cabinet C2</title>

        <para>Distribution cabinet C2 is the lower of the two cabinets
        installed in the forward bulkhead of the lower deck lobby.</para>

        <para>The cabinet receives a 230VAC supply from cabinet C1 via
        isolator (1).</para>

        <para>All circuits in the cabinet are overload and leakage protected
        and are concerened with lighting control for the aft of the ship,
        operation of the ship's PIR sensors, and heating control. The
        distribution cabinet houses a 12VDC power supply for the ship's PIR
        sensors and a 24VDC power supply for light switch circuits on the
        lower deck. The ship's intruder alarm system is installed in the lower
        half of the cabinet.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Distribution cabinet C2</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="left" contentwidth="10cm"
                         fileref="RESOURCES/distribution_cabinet_c2.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
