<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
  <section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>Bilge pumping system</title>

    <para>The vessel is equipped with two electrically operated bilge pumps,
    one in the engine compartment and another in the main compartment. Each
    pump is connected to a float switch which can operate the pump
    automatically when water is detected in the bilge. Each float switch is
    backed-up by an independent water level sensor connected to the ship's
    alarm system.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Bilge system controls</title>

      <para>Each bilge system is operated by a three-position switch located
      at the helm (labelled <keycap>E.ROOM</keycap> and
      <keycap>M.COMP</keycap>):</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>UP POSITION</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The bilge pump and float switch are switched off. In normal
            use the switch should never be left in this position unless the
            vessel is out of the water or the bilge system is being serviced.
            The bilge pump alarm indicator light will illuminate.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>MID POSITION</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The bilge pump and float switch are enabled in automatic
            mode. If the float switch detects water in the bilge the pump will
            start automatically, the helm alarm siren and indicator will
            signal an alert and the bilge pump alarm indicator will
            illuminate.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>DOWN POSITION</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The bilge pump will run, the helm alarm siren and indicator
            will signal an alert and the bilge pump alarm indicator will
            illuminate.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Bilge system alarms</title>

      <para>Each bilge system has an indicator light at the helm which
      illuminates when (i) the bilge system is switched off and (ii) when the
      bilge pump is running. The indicator will flash when the bilge backup
      sensor detects water: typically this means that the float switch has
      failed to activate the bilge pump or the compartment is being inundated
      at a rate beyond the capacity of the bilge pump.</para>

      <para>The helm alarm system will activate when a bilge pump is running
      for whatever reason and also when a backup sensor detects water. The
      audible component of the alarm can be cancelled, but the visual
      component will remain active until the condition causing the alert is
      corrected.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

