<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Maintenance</title>

  <para/>

  <section>
    <title>Hauling out / cradling</title>

    <para>The vessel can be hauled up or lifted out as long as it is
    well-supported whilst on land.</para>

    <para>Lifting out must be accomplished using two slings of minimum width
    15cm. The hull paintwork should be protected from abrasion by putting a
    soft piece of material between the slings and the hull. Take care with the
    guard rails: a narrow sling suspension arm can easily squash them if the
    slings are not threaded through the inside of the rails.</para>

    <para>When placing slings ensure that they do not foul thru-hull sensors
    and the propellor shaft.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Small repairs</title>

    <para>Small repairs to the hull can be made by using a good quality epoxy
    filler and paint. But take care: this only goes if you know what you are
    doing, and the damage is not structural. If in the damaged area there show
    small cracks in the surrounding area or if the damaged area shows fibres
    in the hull or deck structure, get an expert repairman to do the job
    and/or assess the damages. If structural damages occurs while underway,
    try to close off the repair area by taping it.</para>

    <para>Remember that any repair must be as good as the original work if you
    want to keep your boat in good shape.</para>

    <para>DO NOT use silicone-based sealants on any part of the boat.</para>

    <para>When sanding, painting or doing similar work on the boat, remember
    that paintdust and epoxies are to be treated as toxic chemical
    waste.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
