  <section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>Generator</title>

    <para>A 230VAC 12kVA 1500rpm diesel generator is available to provide
    230VAC electrical energy when the vessel is off-grid or when the ship's
    batteries are depleted.</para>

    <para/>

    <section>
      <title>Generator controls</title>

      <para>The generator control panel is located at the helm and offers
      three primary buttons:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>START</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Press to initiate the generator start sequence. The control
            panel will prepare the generator for starting and make up to three
            cranking attempts. If cranking is unsuccessful, check the control
            panel display for diagnostic information and consult the control
            panel manual for further instructions.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>STOP</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Press to stop the generator or cancel auto-start
            mode.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>AUTO</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Press to place the generator in auto-start mode. In
            auto-start mode control of the generator is referred to the ship's
            domestic panel.</para>

            <para>The domestic panel has two switches labelled
            GENERATOR:</para>

            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>left-hand switch</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>In the on position causes the generator to start. The
                  generator will continue running until the switch is turned
                  off or the generator control panel is taken out of
                  auto-start mode.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>right-hand switch</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>In the on position refers generator start control the
                  the ship's battery management system controller. The battery
                  manager will start the generator automatically to recharge
                  the ship's batteries should they become severely
                  depleted.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="generatorelectrics">
      <title>Generator electrics</title>

      <para>The generator operates at 12VDC. A single 120Ah 12VDC cranking
      battery is installed on the port side of the engine room with an
      adjacent battery isolator switch and a dedicated 24VDC battery charger
      which is energised only when the ship is connected to shore or generator
      supply.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Generator exhaust</title>

      <para>The generator has a dry exhaust system routed through a silencer
      and discharging through the transom.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Generator cooling</title>

      <para>The generator engine is indirectly cooled through an immersed heat
      exchanger located in a protected cavity at the port side of the hull.
      The heat exchanger can be serviced from the engine room without the need
      for lift-out or dry-docking.</para>

      <para>A subsidiary primary cooling circuit is used to heat the ship's
      thermal buffer through a heat transfer coil.</para>

      <para>The primary cooling circuit is pumped by a mechanically driven
      engine mounted impeller.</para>

      <para>The generator cabinet is actively cooled by a powerful fan which
      draws air from the engine room, through the cabinet and discharges
      through an insulated pipe at the transom.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

