<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>This manual has been compiled to help you to operate your craft with
  safety and pleasure. It contains details of the craft, the equipment
  supplied or fitted, its systems and information on its operation . Please
  read it carefully, and familiarise yourself with the craft before using
  it.</para>

  <para>Your boat is categorised within the scope of the European Boating
  Directive which identifies maximum sea and wind conditions in which the boat
  is considered safe to operate. Even so, actual sea and weather conditions
  are open to the hazards of a freak wave or gust and only a competent, fit
  and trained crew using a well maintained boat can satisfactorily and safely
  operate the ship. Ensure that the anticipated wind and sea conditions will
  correspond to the design category of your boat, and that you and your crew
  are able to handle the boat in these conditions and are ready to deal with
  the unexpected.</para>

  <para>This owner's manual is not a course on boating safety or seamanship.
  If this is your first craft, or you are changing to a type of craft you are
  not familiar with, for your own comfort and safety, ensure that you obtain
  handling and operating experience before "assuming command" of the craft.
  Your national sailing federation or yacht club will be pleased to advise you
  of local sea schools, or competent instructors.</para>

  <para>This owner's manual is not a detailed maintenance or trouble shooting
  guide. In case of difficulty, refer to the boat builder or its
  representative. Always use trained and competent people for maintenance,
  repairs and modifications. Modifications that may affect the safety
  characteristics of the craft shall be assessed, executed and documented by
  competent people. The boat builder cannot be held responsible for
  modifications which they have not approved.</para>

  <para>NOTE: Any change in the disposition of the masses aboard (for example
  the addition of a fishing tower, a radar, a stowing mast, change of engine,
  etc.) may significantly affect the stability, trim and performance of your
  boat</para>

  <para>Users of this boat are advised that</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>all crew should receive suitable training;</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>the boat should not carry more than the manufacturer's recommended
      load;</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>bilge water should be kept to a minimum;</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>stability is reduced by any weight added high up;</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>in rough weather, portholes, windows, hatches, lockers and
      doorways should be closed to minimise the risk of flooding;</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>stability may be reduced when towing or lifting heavy weights
      using a davit or boom;</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>breaking waves are a serious stability hazard.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>In some countries a driving licence or authorisation are required, or
  specific regulations are in force.</para>

  <para>Always maintain your boat properly and make allowance for the
  deterioration that will occur in time and as a result of heavy use or misuse
  of the boat.</para>

  <para>Any boat – no matter how strong it may be, can be severely damaged if
  not used properly. This is not compatible with safe boating. Always adjust
  the speed and direction of the craft to sea conditions.</para>

  <para>If your boat is fitted with a life raft, read carefully its operating
  manual. The crew should be familiar with the use of all safety equipment
  (harness, flares, life raft, etc..) and emergency manoeuvring (man overboard
  recovery, towing, etc), sailing schools and clubs regularly organise drill
  sessions.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">PLEASE KEEP THIS MANUAL IN A SECURE PLACE, AND
  HAND IT OVER TO THE NEW OWNER WHEN YOU SELL THE CRAFT</emphasis></para>

  <section>
    <title>About this manual</title>

    <para>This manual contains safety precautions that must be observed when
    operating or servicing your boat. Review and understand these
    instructions.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Warnings</title>

      <para>Warnings in this manual are used to indicate:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>immediate hazards which will result in severe injury or
          death;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>hazards or unsafe practises which could result in severe
          personal injury or death;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>hazards or unsafe practises which could result in minor injury
          or property damage.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Symbols</title>

      <para>The following symbols are used within the text to draw your
      attention to important points.</para>

      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                               fileref="../resources/images/DIN_4844-2/mandatory/M018_read_manual.svg"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject></entry>

              <entry>Refer to manufacturer's manual.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                               fileref="../resources/images/DIN_4844-2/rescue/E010_escape_route_right.svg"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject></entry>

              <entry>Escape route</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                               fileref="../resources/images/DIN_4844-2/prohibition/P002_no_naked_flames.svg"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject></entry>

              <entry>No open flame or smoking</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                               fileref="../resources/images/DIN_4844-2/warning/W026_risk_of_hot_surface.svg"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject></entry>

              <entry>Warning: risk of high temperature</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                               fileref="../resources/images/DIN_4844-2/warning/W008_risk_of_electrocution.svg"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject></entry>

              <entry>Warning: risk of electrical shock</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                               fileref="../resources/images/DIN_4844-2/warning/W001_risk_of_fire.svg"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject></entry>

              <entry>Warning: risk of fire</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                               fileref="../resources/images/DIN_4844-2/warning/W000_general.svg"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject></entry>

              <entry>Warning: unclassified</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                               fileref="../resources/images/DIN_4844-2/warning/W002_risk_of_explosion.svg"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject></entry>

              <entry>Danger of explosion</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                               fileref="../resources/images/DIN_4844-2/warning/W025_risk_of_remote_start.svg"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject></entry>

              <entry>Warning: remotely started equipment</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                               fileref="../resources/images/DIN_4844-2/fire/F005_fire_extinguisher.svg"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject></entry>

              <entry>Fire extinguisher</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Drawings</title>

      <para>Any drawings supplied with this manual are incorporated into the
      text of the manual as far as practicably possible. Possibly some
      drawings are inserted behind the annexes.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Manufacturer's manuals</title>

      <para>The manuals of the equipment supplied with the ship are bundled
      and supplied together with this manual and are considered to form an
      integral part of it. For a list of supplied manufacturer's manuals see
      <xref linkend="bibliography"/>. Reference to manufacturer manuals in
      text is often accompanied by the symbol <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                       fileref="../resources/images/DIN_4844-2/mandatory/M018_read_manual.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>.</para>

      <para>Text of manufacturer supplied manuals concerning maintenance etc.
      always prevails over the text in this owner's manual.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
