<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Ethernet LAN</title>

  <para>Ethernet LANs support a range of ship services, providing client
  access for information displays, virtual control panels, VoIP deck
  communication, map and NIS services and audio and video entertainment. The
  general arrangement of LAN components is illustrated in the following
  schematic.</para>

  <para><figure>
      <title>Schematic of Beatrice's Ethernet LAN</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentwidth="15cm"
                     fileref="resources/images/ethernet_lan.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure></para>

  <para>A power over Ethernet <emphasis role="bold">Switch</emphasis>
  establishes a wired Ethernet LAN that connects important servers, desktops
  and installed equipment like IP cameras. Devices in this network are
  assigned static IP addresses in the 192.168.1.0/24 sub-net.</para>

  <para>This basic LAN is sufficient to provide a platform for operating the
  ship, but normally it will be extended by one or more wireless mesh networks
  created by <emphasis role="bold">Helm Router</emphasis> and <emphasis
  role="bold">Saloon Access Point</emphasis>. A wireless network with SSID
  “beatrice” uses the same 192.168.1.0/24 sub-net as the wired LAN and clients
  have unrestricted access to all on-board services. A second wireless network
  “beatrice-guest” uses a different sub-net with restricted bandwidth and
  limited access to devices on the primary LAN. Client devices on the mesh
  networks are assigned IP addresses by <emphasis role="bold">Helm
  Router</emphasis>‘s DHCP service with some clients (for example the ship’s
  audio visual devices) receiving fixed addresses.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Helm Router</emphasis>‘s WAN interface can be
  connected through <emphasis role="bold">A/B Switch</emphasis> to either
  <emphasis role="bold">WiFi Router</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">4G
  Router</emphasis> facilitating access to the Internet for the whole network.
  Internet access via <emphasis role="bold">WiFi Router</emphasis> is only
  feasible when the vessel has access to a suitable shore-based WiFi access
  point; when the vessel is cruising the only viable means of Internet access
  will be via <emphasis role="bold">4G Router</emphasis> which, in an case,
  seeks to maintain a permanent cellular data connection.</para>

  <para>Typically, all the various network routers, switches and access points
  should be powered whenever the vessel is in commission.</para>

  <para>User operation of the LAN reduces to selecting the WAN connection type
  (<emphasis role="bold">A/B Switch</emphasis> can be remotely operated by the
  helm panel [WiFi] switch) and visiting <emphasis role="bold">WiFi
  Router</emphasis>‘s configuration interface in order to establish a
  connection to a harbour access point. The mesh network is implemented on
  Google WiFi hardware and can be monitored and configured using the “Google
  Home” App.</para>

  <para>See this table for an inventory of (and more detailed information on)
  LAN devices which have static and fixed IP addresses.</para>
</section>
