<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Fuel system</title>

  <para>Refer to <xref linkend="fluid-storage-and-handling"/> for a system
  overview.</para>

  <para>Twin steel storage tanks are integrated into the vessel's hull
  midships. Fuel from the 1800 litre port-side tank is used exclusively for
  main-engine propulsion whilst fuel from the 1800 litre starboard tank is
  used exclusively for domestic heating and electricity generation. The two
  storage tanks are not interconnected, but barbs and valves are provided
  which would allow tank interconnection in an emergency.</para>

  <para>Fuel filling, distribution, return and tank venting is through
  metallic pipes and non-metallic hoses of sturdy construction. All
  connections to (moving) machinery is made with flexible hoses.</para>

  <para>Water separators and filters are placed in front of each fuel
  consumer. The generator fuel supply line is assisted by a lift pump mounted
  inside the generator cabinet.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Filling the tanks</title>

    <para>Two filling points clearly marked "DIESEL" are located in a recess
    on the starboard side of the vessel just forwards of the wheelhouse. The
    left-hand filler connects to the domestic (starboard-side) fuel tank; the
    right-hand filler connects to the propulsion (port-side) fuel tank.</para>

    <para>In some regulatory authorities it is permissible to use reduced tax
    fuel ('red diesel' in Europe) for domestic purposes. DO NOT fill the
    vessel's propulsion tank with red-diesel. The procedure for filling a tank
    is:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Determine the type of fuel to be taken on (red or white diesel)
        and so identify the associated tank and filler location.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Check the appropriate tank level using one of the vessel's
        display gauges and so determine how much fuel can be taken on.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Open the correct filler cap.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Start filling the tank: begin with a steady to moderate
        flow.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Check the tank level by monitoring a display gauge.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Do not fill the tank to its maximum: gauges are not exactly
        accurate and room should be left for expansion of the fuel and
        contraction of the tank. Filling to 90% capacity is sensible.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Replace and close the filler cap.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Clean up any spills</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Make an entry in the ship's log.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                     fileref="resources/images/DIN_4844-2/warning/W000_general.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject> Diesel oil must be treated as chemical waste and an
    absorbant cloth should be to hand when filling the ship's tanks.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Water separators and filters</title>

    <para>Water separators and filters are located in the engine
    compartment.</para>

    <para>The main engine is served by two water separators: the separator in
    use is selected by a valve which allows a changeover should one separator
    become clogged or require service. The generator and boiler each have
    single water separators. Any water collected by the separators should be
    regularly drained.</para>

    <para>Fuel filters are located adjacent to or mounted on the main engine,
    generator and boiler.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                     fileref="resources/images/DIN_4844-2/warning/W000_general.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject> Water separator and fuel filter elements must be
    regularly changed.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                     fileref="resources/images/DIN_4844-2/mandatory/M018_read_manual.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject> FILL ME IN</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Tank level monitoring</title>

    <para>Each tank is equipped with an electronic tank level monitoring
    system consisting of a hydrostatic tank level sender which broadcasts
    messages onto the ship's domestic NMEA 2000 bus. Tank level data can be
    displayed on screens located at the helm, domestic panel and
    elsewhere.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                     fileref="resources/images/DIN_4844-2/warning/W000_general.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject> Variations in tank level readings are possible due
    to conditions of trim, list, seaway and callibration.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                     fileref="resources/images/DIN_4844-2/warning/W000_general.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject> Tank level readings require <guilabel>NMEA BUS
    0</guilabel> to be enabled on the ship's domestic panel.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                     fileref="resources/images/DIN_4844-2/mandatory/M018_read_manual.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject> <citation>mare1</citation></para>
  </section>
</section>
