<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Space heating, cooling and hot water</title>

  <para>The vessel is equipped with an integrated hydronic space heating and
  cooling system (SHCS) (see <xref
  linkend="heating-system-overview"/>).</para>

  <para>SHCS is bi-modal: at any one time the system can be in either heating
  mode or cooling mode and it is not possible to heat one space on the ship
  whilst simultaneously cooling another.</para>

  <para>The operating mode of SHCS is selected by the <keycap>CHILLER</keycap>
  switch at the domestic panel: when the switch is OFF, the system is in
  heating mode; when it is ON, the system is in cooling mode.<footnote>
      <para>In fact, the ship's central chiller can operate in reverse cycle,
      so it is possible to operate the HVAC system in cooling mode in a way
      which generates space heating.</para>
    </footnote>Domestic hot water is available irrespective of the operating
  mode of SHCS.</para>

  <para>The vessel has a mix of fancoil and radiator heat exchangers:
  radiators only operate in heating mode whilst fancoil units will operate in
  both heating mode and cooling mode.</para>

  <para>The primary heat source on the vessel is a large thermal buffer,
  consisting of a well-insulated mass of heated water, and in order for the
  ship to be heated and hot-water to be available, the buffer must be
  maintained at an appropriate operating temperature.</para>

  <para>The primary heat sink on the vessel is a refrigeration unit capable of
  chilling the circulating hydronic fluid and so allowing fancoil units to
  blow cold air.</para>

  <section xml:id="heating">
    <title>Thermal buffer</title>

    <para>The thermal buffer holds 250 litres of hydronic fluid which acts as
    the heat source for space heating and domestic hot water.<footnote>
        <para>One benefit of using a buffer is that its high heat capacity
        ensures that the diesel boiler runs more efficiently with less cycling
        than would occur if the boiler were directly driving the heating or
        hot water systems; a further benefit is that once heated the buffer
        can produce many times its own volume of domestic hot water.</para>
      </footnote>Hydronic fluid in the thermal buffer stratifies by
    temperature: the hottest fluid at the top of the buffer and the coldest at
    the bottom. Hydronic fluid for domestic water heating is taken from the
    top of the buffer and fluid used for space heating is taken from the
    middle of the buffer. Cooled fluid is returned to the bottom of the store
    in order to preserve stratification.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Operating characteristics</title>

      <para>The buffer is designed to operate at a maximum temperature of 85C
      and it can be heated (recharged) from the sources shown in the following
      table.</para>

      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Heat source</entry>

              <entry>Time for full recharge</entry>

              <entry>Time for HW availability</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1kW immersion heater</entry>

              <entry>Several hours</entry>

              <entry>~ 30 minutes</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>2kW immersion heater</entry>

              <entry>~ 1 hour</entry>

              <entry>~ 20 minutes</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Diesel boiler</entry>

              <entry>10 minutes</entry>

              <entry>Instantaneous</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Waste heat from generator</entry>

              <entry>20 minutes</entry>

              <entry>&lt; 5 minutes</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Waste heat from engine</entry>

              <entry>20 minutes</entry>

              <entry>&lt; 5 minutes</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>

      <para>Typically the hydronic fluid in the thermal buffer rapidly assumes
      a temperature gradient and it will be capable of driving the hot-water
      system and, to a lesser extent, SHCS in less time than would be required
      for a full recharge.</para>

      <para>Exactly what constitutes a recharge using the boiler is determined
      by three thermostats mounted on the thermal store and one mounted on the
      boiler.</para>

      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Thermostat</entry>

              <entry>Set point/C (initial configuration)</entry>

              <entry>Remark</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Boiler</entry>

              <entry>80</entry>

              <entry>Determines the absolute maximum temperature of the
              thermal buffer.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>T1 (top thermostat)</entry>

              <entry>50</entry>

              <entry>Used to switch on the boiler when the recharge is
              intended to support hot water production.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>T2 (middle thermostat)</entry>

              <entry>60</entry>

              <entry>Used to switch on the boiler when the recharge is
              intended to support space heating.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>T3 (lower thermostat)</entry>

              <entry>60</entry>

              <entry>Used to switch off the boiler.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>

      <para>T3 determines the 'depth' of buffer recharge: the higher the set
      point the more heat is absorbed in the store in any given mode. Tweaking
      the thermostat settings for a particular domestic pattern of usage is an
      interesting exercise.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Operating the thermal buffer</title>

      <para>The user can choose how and when to recharge the thermal buffer
      and typically this choice will be based upon the demand for heat and the
      economy of an available heat source. For example, if the demand is
      solely for hot water, then a fully charged buffer may continue to
      satisfy this demand for up to 48h with no intervention and indefinitely
      with occasional, low-level, energy input. Equally, if there is a demand
      for space heating throughout the boat, then the diesel boiler might be
      the obvious recharge source although availability of shore power and a
      low or zero space heating demand might make immersion heating a suitable
      alternative. For a vessel navigating norther Europe in the summer it is
      unlikely that any additional heat input to the buffer will be necessary
      over and above that supplied by the main engine.</para>

      <para>The domestic panel controls which operate the buffer are:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><keycap>IMMERSION 1kW</keycap></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Operates the 1kW immersion heater which is the located
            towards the top of the thermal buffer and can effectively prepare
            the system for hot water generation only.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><keycap>IMMERSION 2kW</keycap></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Operates the 2kW immersion heater which is located further
            down the the thermal buffer and can quickly prepare the system for
            hot water generation only.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><keycap>IMMERSION 1kW</keycap> and <keycap>IMMERSION
          2kW</keycap></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Running both immersion heaters simultaneously will rapidly
            prepare the buffer for hot water generation and can also support
            low demand space heating.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><keycap>BOILER</keycap></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Recharging the buffer using the boiler supports immediate
            hot water generation (even when the store is at ambient
            temperature) and continuous high-load heating demands.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Domestic hot water</title>

    <para>Domestic hot water is available any time the thermal buffer is
    charged.</para>

    <para>A fully charged buffer can support up to 48 hours of solely domestic
    hot water demand before requiring a recharge. If the domestic panel
    <keycap>BOILER</keycap> switch is ON, then channel 2 of the four-channel
    time controller located in the galley can be used to schedule or initiate
    an immediate recharge of the thermal buffer.</para>

    <para>Hot water is generated by a plate heat exchanger with its primary
    circuit fed from the thermal buffer and its secondary circuit fed directly
    from the hydrophore. The output of the plate heat exchanger passes through
    a blending valve to give a comfortable domestic hot-water temperature. An
    independent, intelligent, hot-water loop can be used to make hot water
    available instantaneously at each outlet.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Operating the hot water system</title>

      <para>The domestic panel controls which operate the domestic hot water
      system are:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><keycap>THERMAL STORE</keycap></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Operates the plate heat exchanger system. This ensures that
            the pump driving the primary heat exchange circuit is enabled: a
            flow switch will start the pump when a hot water outlet is opened
            or when the hot-water loop is enabled. This control should be left
            in the ON position when the ship is occupied.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><keycap>HOT WATER LOOP</keycap></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Enables the hot water loop. The hot water loop is driven by
            an intelligent pump which learns periods of hot-water demand and
            only runs to anticipate these.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Using the boiler for hot-water generation</title>

      <para>If the boiler is the preferred recharge source for the buffer,
      then channel 2 of the four-channel time controller located in the galley
      can be used to schedule recharge events or initiate an ad-hoc
      recharge.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Space heating</title>

    <para>Space heating is available any time the thermal buffer is charged,
    but the demands of heating the entire ship will rapidly deplete the buffer
    if one or more means of continuous recharge is not available.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Operating the heating system</title>

      <para>The heating system will only be available if the domestic panel
      <keycap>CHILLER</keycap> control is OFF.</para>

      <para>The heating system circulation pump is operated by channel 1 of
      the four-channel time controller located in the galley. If the heating
      demand is high and neither the generator or main engine are running,
      then the thermal store should be configured for recharge from the diesel
      boiler by setting the domestic panel <keycap>BOILER</keycap> switch to
      ON. If the heating demand is low and shore or generator power is
      available, then using both immersion heaters to recharge the store is
      feasible.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Space cooling</title>

    <para>The cooling system will only be available if the domestic panel
    <keycap>CHILLER</keycap> control is set to ON.</para>

    <para>The chiller system control panel is located in the galley. Refer to
    the chiller system documentation for details of operation.</para>
  </section>
</section>
