<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Waste water system</title>

  <para>The waste water system consists of a 1100 litre holding tank, which
  accumulates grey water waste from sinks, basins and showers and black water
  waste from WCs. The holding tank is vented through the hull via a charcoal
  filter.</para>

  <para>WCs pump waste directly to the holding tank. All other waste water
  flows by gravity to sumps positioned around the vessel which automatically
  pump collected waste to the holding tank.</para>

  <para>The holding tank can be emptied through a deck pump-out connection or
  by use of the ship's own discharge pump.</para>

  <para>Refer to <xref linkend="fluid-storage-and-handling"/> for a system
  overview.</para>

  <para><inlinemediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                   fileref="resources/images/DIN_4844-2/warning/W000_general.svg"/>
      </imageobject>
    </inlinemediaobject> Never let the holding tank become too full:
  overfilling can cause a system malfunction with overflow of sewage water
  into the bilge and backflow into the rerst of the system.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Heads</title>

    <para>WCs pump macerated waste directly to the holding tank each time the
    'flush' function is activated.</para>

    <para>The WCs operate at 230VAC and are supplied via circuit-breakers in
    distribution cabinets C1 and C4. The WCs should normally remain powered
    whenever the vessel is in use.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                     fileref="resources/images/DIN_4844-2/warning/W008_risk_of_electrocution.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject> WC units operate at 230VAC, unplug from mains
    before servicing.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                     fileref="resources/images/DIN_4844-2/mandatory/M018_read_manual.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject> sani2</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Sumps</title>

    <para>Four sealed waste water sumps are located in the bilge at various
    locations around the vessel. Each sump contains a float switch which
    detects when the sump is full and energises a pump to dischargethe
    contents of the sump to the holding tank.</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>SUMP1</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Collects waste water from the guest cabin shower and from the
          lower-deck fancoil unit condensate drain. The unit is accessed
          through a hatch in the office floor.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>SUMP2</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Collects waste water from washing machine, dishwasher, galley
          sink, day head basin, saloon fancoil unit condensate drain and the
          lower-deck porthole condensation drains. The unit is accessed
          through the crawlspace beyond the lower companionway.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>SUMP3</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Collects waste water from the master cabin en-suite basin and
          shower. The unit is accessed through the crawlspace beyond the lower
          companionway.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>SUMP4</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Collects waste water from the master cabin fancoil unit
          condensate drain. The unit is accessed through the hatch under the
          master cabin bed.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>The sumps operate at 230VAC and are supplied via circuit-breakers in
    distribution cabinets C1 and C4. The sumps should normally remain powered
    whenever the vessel is in use.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                     fileref="resources/images/DIN_4844-2/warning/W008_risk_of_electrocution.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject> Sump units operate at 230VAC, unplug from mains
    before servicing.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                     fileref="resources/images/DIN_4844-2/mandatory/M018_read_manual.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject> sani1</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Tank level monitoring</title>

    <para>The holding tank is equipped with an electronic tank level
    monitoring system consisting of a hydrostatic tank level sender which
    broadcasts messages onto the ship's domestic NMEA 2000 bus. Tank level
    data can be displayed on screens located at the helm, domestic panel and
    elsewhere.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                     fileref="resources/images/DIN_4844-2/warning/W000_general.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject> Variations in tank level readings are possible due
    to conditions of trim, list, seaway and callibration.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                     fileref="resources/images/DIN_4844-2/warning/W000_general.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject> Tank level readings require <guilabel>NMEA BUS
    0</guilabel> to be enabled on the ship's domestic panel.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                     fileref="resources/images/DIN_4844-2/mandatory/M018_read_manual.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject> <citation>mare1</citation></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Empting the holding tank</title>

    <para>The holding tank can be emptied at a suitable shore-side pump-out
    facility or by pumping out using the ship's own discharge pump.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Emptying the holding tank at a pump-out station</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Splash the area around the pump-out DECK FITTING with water to
          prevent any possible spillage adhering to the deck.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Close the tank DISCHARGE VALVE.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Open the tank SUCTION VALVE</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Open the DECK FITTING and connect the suction hose from the
          shore pump-out facility. Make the sure the connection between the
          inner surface of the DECK FITTING and the suction hose is secure and
          leak free.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Start the shore-side suction and allow to complete.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Disconnect suction hose.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Close DECK FITTING.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Wash down deck if necessary and wash hands.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Close SUCTION VALVE</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Make entry in ship's log.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Emptying the holding tank by pumping it out</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Make sure that the vessel is in a body of water where pumping
          out is permitted and that discharge will not inconvenience
          anyone.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Open DISCHARGE VALVE and SEA COCK.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Operate the WASTE switch at the helm panel to start the
          discharge pump. The helm alarm will signal an alert whilst the pump
          is running: the audible component of the alert can be silenced, but
          the visual alert will continue until the discharge pump is switched
          off.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Listen for a change in pump resonance which indicates the tank
          is empty or monitor progress of the discharge on a tank level
          display. Discharging a full holding tank will take over 30 minutes.
          Do not let the discharge pump run dry unnecessarily.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Switch off the waste pump.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Close DISCHARGE VALVE and SEA COCK.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Make an entry in the ship's log.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Emptying the holding tank by pumping it out automatically</title>

      <para>The vessel has an automatic discharge system integrated into the
      ship's NMEA 2000 controller. The automatic mode is selected from the
      <keycap>WASTE</keycap> switch at the helm panel and causes the
      controller to continuously monitor the waste level in the holding tank:
      at 90% capacity the controller will start the wast discharge pump,
      stopping it again when the tank reaches 10% capacity. Whilst the pump is
      in operation the helm alarm will signal an alert.</para>

      <para><inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentwidth="0.5cm"
                       fileref="resources/images/DIN_4844-2/warning/W000_general.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> Ensure that the DISCHARGE VALVE and SEA COCK
      remain open whilst the discharge system is set to automatic.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
